Preliminary Guide to the Donald R. Lehman papers, 1964-2000 MS2292.UA
Special Collections Research Center, The George Washington University
Donald R. Lehman papers
1964-2000
1970-1995
Special Collections Research Center, The George Washington University
MS2292.UA
17 Linear Feet 15 record cartons (2 over-size).
Dr. Donald R. Lehman (1940-) served more than thirty-eight years as a faculty member and administrator at The George Washington University. Dr. Lehman's major roles at the University included Chair of the Physics Department, founder of the Center for Nuclear Studies, Associate Vice President for Research and Graduate Studies, and Executive Vice President for Academic Affairs. Materials in the collection date from 1964 to 2000, with the bulk of the material dating between 1970 and 1995. The collection includes manuscripts and other preparatory materials for Dr. Lehman's master's thesis, doctoral dissertation, and publications; notebooks; correspondence; article reprints; notes; theoretical work; research files; and teaching materials related predominately to Dr. Lehman's work as a physicist.
Conditions Governing Access
This collection is open for research.
Arrangement
This collection is unprocessed and remains in the orignal order imposed by the collection's creator. Additional time may be required to use the collection. Please see Special Collections staff for assistance.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Dr. Donald R. Lehman, 2011 (2011.029).
Scope and Contents
This collection contains the personal papers of Dr. Donald R. Lehman. Materials in the collection date from 1964 to 2000, with the bulk of the material dating between 1970 and 1995. The collection includes manuscripts and other preparatory materials for Dr. Lehman's master's thesis, doctoral dissertation, and publications; notebooks; correspondence; article reprints; notes; theoretical work; research files; work with graduate students and other physicists, and teaching materials related predominately to Dr. Lehman's work as a physicist.
Biographical / Historical
Dr. Donald R. Lehman (1940-) retired from The George Washington University on 31 December 2010 after serving more than thirty-eight years as a faculty member and administrator.
Dr. Lehman earned a BA in Physics from Rutgers University in 1962, an MS in Space Physics from the Air Force Institute of Technology in 1964, and a Ph.D. in Theoretical Physics from The George Washington University in 1970. Lehman joined the GW faculty as an Assistant Professor of Physics in 1972, becoming a fully Professor in 1982. He was made Chair of the Department of Physics in 1987, and he founded the Center for Nuclear Studies at the University in 1990.
From 1993 to 1996, Dr. Lehman held the position of Associate Vice President for Research and Graduate Studies. He was appointed Vice President for Academic Affairs in 1996, and served in this role until 2002 when he was made the George Gamow Professor of Theoretical Physics. He was the Executive Vice President for Academic Affairs from 2003 to 2010, and in 2010 he served as Senior Advisor to the President until his retirement.
Related Materials
An oral history interview with Dr. Lehman, conducted in 2011 by Assistant University Archivist Ashley Locke, is available in the University Archives Oral History collection, MS0371. The interview is available online at: http://gwdspace.wrlc.org:8180/xmlui/handle/38989/c01p2nh6b
Records for the office of the Vice President for Academic Affairs are located in RG0004, and records for the Physics Department are in RG0077.
Bib#
8908890
Photodisintegration; Nuclear physics; Physics; Theoretical physics; George Washington University--Faculty; Lehman, Donald Richard; George Washington University
- UP0001, 1964-1992 (Box UP0001)
  Scope and Contents
  1) Research work, drafts, and final version of AFIT Master's thesis (1964) 2) Drafts and final version of GWU Ph.D. dissertation (1970) 3) Notebooks containing notes from colloquia, special seminars, and physics meetigns attended starting in 1971 through 1992.
- UP0002, circa 1985-1994 (Box UP0002)
  Research work and materials from the late 1980s and early 1990s.
  1) Misc. correspondence 2) Materials leading to published manuscritps (drafts) 3) DOE Panel Review materials, 1994
- UP0003, circa 1970-1975 (Box UP0003)
  1) Nuclear four-body problems (reprints and notes from preparatory ready and study) 2) Photodisintegration of 3He - original notes and work from the early 1970s 3) Photodisintegration of 3He and the iso-spin suppression noted through sum rules by Barton
- UP0004, undated (Box UP0004)
  1) Initial theoretical work on the three-body model of 6Li - five-equation model 2) Doctoral dissertation work on the theory of the electrodisintegration of 3He and 3H 3) Theoretical work on the building of the full three-body model of 6Li including 6Li > a + d and 6Li > p + (na)
- UP0005, 1994-1995 and undated (Box UP0005)
  This box contains various files containing work/background materials for writing manuscripts. These files cover a wide range of years. In addition to these files, the material for the 1994-1995 Academic Program Review of the Physics Department is also included in one file and one notebook.
- UP0006, undated (Box UP0006)
  1) Materials from major talks on research work 2) Materials for manuscripts that were submitted for publication in journals 3) Two research notebooks on the Koike, Lehman, Maximon, and Parke collaboration with respect to the testing of the EST method for representing realistic NN interactions in the calculation of the three-body, bound-state binding energy.
- UP0007, 1988-1992 (Box UP0007)
  1) Materials associated with Annual Reviews of Nuclear Science article - 1988 2) Materials from preparation of Paris 90 talk and article 3) Review talk on Electromagnetic Few-Body Problems - Photonuclear Gordon Conference - 9 to 14 August 1992
- UP0008, undated (Box UP0008)
  The full content of this box is associated with the two-body photodisintegration of the 3He and the inverse reaction of polarized deuteron radiative capture on protons [1H(d,y)3He] into 3He. This is work that was done in collaboration with Antonio Fonseca [Lisbon, Portugal].
- UP0009, undated (Box UP0009)
  Research Notebooks 1) 6Li electromagnetic form factors in connection with Ali Eskandarian's dissertation work 2) Product integration and integrals containing spherical Bessel functions 3) 6Li > p + (na) work through (p,2p) and e,e'p) reactions in connection with Carol Chrisou's dissertation work 4) 6He beta decay 5) Notebook on some work with Ben Gibson
- UP0010, undated (Box UP0010)
  Research Notebooks 1) A=6 Shell Model from three-body model 2) Coulomb interaction in momentum space - three-body problem 3) Extensive work on asymptotic normalization constants including the effects of Coulomb
- UP0011, undated (Box UP0011)
  1) Teaching materials from undergraduate courses and graduate courses 2) Some trip folders of trips association with physics conferences, physics talks, and special visits to other universities.
- UP0012, 1964-1992 (Box UP0012)
  1) Materials from graduate coursework at AFIT and The George Washington University (covering about 1962-1964 for AFIT and 1965-1968 for GWU) 2) Some written materials from the period of being at the Air Force Office of Scientific Research (1964-1968) 3) Personal correspondence folders for the period 1972 to 1992. Much of this correspondence pertains to reviews of manuscripts for journals, and propsals for funding agencies, along with some pertaining to exchanges about various physics topics with individuals at other universities and laboratories.
- UP0013, 1964-1992 (Box UP0013)
  Research Notebooks 1) Work on the theory of few-body hyper-nuclei 2) Work on polarization observables for d + p > 3He + Y 3) Work on projecting forbidden bound states in the A=6 bound nuclei 4) Work with Mohamed Najmeddine on few-body physics - in particular, the halo nucleus 11Li. A copy of his dissertation is included.
- UP0014, 1987 and undated (Box UP0014)
  Research notebooks and files.
  This box contains the work of Lehman and Ph.D. student John Woloshek. Present are Lehman's records associated with Mr. Woloshek as a graduate student. In addition, there are four notebooks of work and research papers that contain copies of his work and the original notes of Lehman's parallel work connected to Woloshek's efforts. In addition, there is a copy of Kazuya Miyagawa's thesis (1987) and a paper by him and others concerning d-a scattering including absorption effects. These papers served as the basis for a generalization pursued at my suggestion by Mr. Woloshek in an attempt to understand the quadrupole moment of 6Li within the context of a three-body model that included N-a interactions with a coupled channel to N-a*, where a* was created to allow for the presence of inelasticity in the N-a interaction.
- UP0015, 1969-2000 (Box UP0015)
  2 binders containing journal articles, published invited talks, and a few abstracts of contributed conference talks by Lehman. Each publication is followed by a list of citations of that article including an abstract (when available) of the article in which the citation occurs. The sources for finding the citations are indicated on the summary sheets at the beginning of the two binders.